Guide to the Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council records 1971-1974
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council records
1971-1974
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council (Walla Walla, Wash.)
WCMss.029
0.8 linear feet 2 boxes
This collection contains administrative records, budget proposals and reports of the Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council, which organized and implemented a number of programs associated with drug abuse education and prevention.
Collection is open for research.
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown.
Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council (DAC) was appointed by the County and City councilmen in December 1969, by the request of Governor Daniel Evans. The DAC studied local problems for one year with youth, college and community leaders. After the year-long study, in 1971, the DAC commenced monthly meetings to assess alcohol and drug use, implement education and prevention programs, and monitor community progress. Programs included community education, speakers and panels, and targeted youth and schools. The DAC encouraged the participation of youth in their activities, and students served on the Drug Abuse Council.
The DAC was closely connected with the New Morning Guild, or the New Morning Inn, a drop-in-center for youth. This program was supported by the Walla Walla School District and the Council. According to reports, the Guild served approximately 100 youth, hosting over 1500 visits per month. New Morning facilitated craft workshops, educational tutoring, presentations, employment counseling, and agency referrals.
The DAC was dissolved in August 1974. In the foreclosure statement, the City Council announced its formal support of substance-abuse programs, such as New Morning, and school and community education.
The collection contains official documents, meeting notes, clippings, and formal reports regarding the Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council. Particularly interesting are the organization's financial information and professionally prepared reports. The minutes and proceedings record the history of a local social service agency which begins, following national trends of drug education and policy, and ends in controversy over the capacity of city and county organizations to adequately address drug-abuse problem.
Bowker, Lee H.
Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council (Walla Walla, Wash.)
Washington (State)
- Corporate Records, 1971-1974; 1
  This series includes two scrapbooks containing founding documents, the original 1971 report and assessment on drug-use/abuse, annual reports, meeting minutes, clippings from the Union-Bulletin and other publications, community advertisements, and reports from the New Morning Guild. These scrapbooks are loosely ordered by chronology and original order has been maintained. Also included in this series is a large amount of budget information, including spending records, proposals, and correspondence. Several letters to a law firm are included, along with minutes appearing outside the compiled scrapbook.
  - Records, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Object 1)
  - Records, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Object 2)
  - Correspondence and loose minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Budget information, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- County Drug Project Reports, 1972-1974, undated; 2
  In 1974, a group of Whitman College professors led by Lee H. Bowker, Ph.D, secured a grant from the National Institute of Mental Health. They completed a number of studies which were central to controversy within the Drug Abuse Council. These studies were never published and contain general surveys, anthropological studies, and estimates/records the attitude towards drug use in Walla Walla during the early 1970s.
  - "Getting Off": patterns and conceptions of drug use and abuse, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - College student drug use and related factors in three rural colleges, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Drug use among adults in Walla Walla County, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Drug use in our schools, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Drug use of a subculture in Walla Walla County, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Final report: To use or not to use: drug use and abuse in a rural county, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Motives for Drug Use: an application of Cohen's typology, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The social agency network in Walla Walla County, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bowker Papers, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Whitman professor, Lee Bowker, secured a grant with the National Institute of Mental Health in 1972. Though Whitman College was the grantee agency, Bowker intended to work in cooperation with the Walla Walla Drug Abuse Council. This folder contains Bowker's records, grant proposal and communication with Whitman College.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1971-1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Report of the Walla Walla County-City Drug Abuse Council, 1971 January (Box 2, Folder 13)